Emily!
You're the medical examiner?
Mr. Rose?
I'm sorry, Mr. Rose...
...but I cannot state conclusively...
...that the cause of death
was natural.
Your daughter, she...
Excuse me, Father?
Father Moore.
You'll have to come with me.
- Father Moore!
- Will you plead guilty?
- Tell us about the exorcism!
- Over here, Father Moore!
We're at Crescent County Courthouse.
We show you Father Richard Moore...
- What about the parents?
- They're not talking to the police.
Do we charge them?
No. Even the priest admits
he ran the show.
We need a Christian on this.
Preferably a Catholic.
Somebody that knows this shit
inside out...
...and who the public will see
as unbiased.
We're going after a holy man here.
Ethan Thomas.
He's not Catholic, though.
Methodist, I think.
But the guy practically lives at church.
Choir, teaches Sunday school.
He's no choirboy in the courtroom.
I've seen him tear people up.
He's a shrewd son of a bitch.
All right, pull him off whatever
he's doing. He's lead prosecutor.
There's ambition. She never stops.
She even works while she drinks.
- Gentlemen, you know Erin Bruner.
- Of course.
- Hello.
- I was so sure Van Hopper would fry...
...but you proved me wrong, lady.
The system worked, that's all.
Gentlemen, you'll excuse us,
will you?
Have you seen the news
about this priest?
I heard something about an exorcism
gone bad, but I don't know the details.
The DA charged him
with negligent homicide.
They offered a very reasonable plea
bargain, but the priest turned it down.
Do not ask me to take this...
The archdiocese
specifically requested you.
- Why me?
- They followed the Van Hopper trial.
They think you're smart...
...and convincing.
They want you to ask the priest
to reconsider.
Well, what if he won't?
This sounds like a quagmire.
If I'm smart, I'll leave it alone.
Erin, the Van Hopper case
got you back on the fast track.
Once again, you're a rising star.
- Chivas, neat, please.
- Tanqueray martini, dry.
- What are you saying?
- I'm saying, you do this for me...
...and the rising star keeps rising.
The case is yours.
And just how high
do I get to rise this time?
I've been junior partner
for too long now, Karl.
- It's not like other firms haven't called.
- Erin...
I want my name on the door,
right next to yours.
Okay.
Try to get the deal.
If the priest won't
and this goes to trial...
...the archdiocese feels he could
be an embarrassment.
So under no circumstances
is he to testify.
No, of course.
If I'd put Van Hopper on the stand...
...he'd be marking time on death row
instead of sunbathing in Miami.
His tab.
Good morning, I'm Erin Bruner.
May I sit down?
They brought the chair
for my public defender.
I guess they left it when they decided
I wasn't going to kill myself with it.
My firm represents the archdiocese.
Yes.
Yes, I was expecting them
to send someone.
- Why did they choose you?
- I wanted this case.
- So you like the spotlight?
- I'm used to it.
I defended James Van Hopper.
And now you've come
to further your celebrity.
No.
I'm here to make senior partner
at my firm.
- Are you a Catholic?
- No.
I'm an agnostic, I guess.
I'm not really sure.
If you're not sure, then you are one.
I don't think you're the right attorney.
I'll stick with my public defender.
He can't get the DA
to get you a better deal. I can.
I won't be making
any plea agreement.
If you don't, the archdiocese
won't post your bail.
You'll be stuck in here for the trial.
Do you understand how long
they can put you away?
It's been explained to me.
The DA's office doesn't like it when
religion holds itself above the law.
And this prosecutor,
Ethan Thomas?
You're gonna need somebody
hungry and smart...
...and aggressive
to even have a chance.
What would your strategy be to defend
me against such a formidable man?
- That depends.
- On what?
On how you wanna be defended.
What's your main concern,
other than staying out of jail?
- Is it how you're being portrayed?
- I don't care about my reputation.
I'm not afraid of jail.
What I care about
is telling Emily Rose's story.
I want people to hear
what only I can tell.
And what is that?
What really happened to Emily...
...and why.
If I let you defend me...
...will you promise to let me testify and
tell the truth about what happened?
And what is the truth you would tell?
That the ritual killed her?
- Was it your fault she died?
- No.
All right.
Then I'll let you tell her story.
But only if you agree to let me do
whatever else it takes to win.
You're not used to
this kind of place.
I'm sure our life is very strange
to you.
Not so strange.
I grew up in a little town.
But our house wasn't as nice
or as big as this.
My mother, she raised me alone.
She was a schoolteacher,
so we had very little money.
What a wonderful thing to be.
That was Emily's dream,
to be a teacher.
That's why she went away
to the university.
A lot of cats live here.
There are...
...11 now, I think.
Emily always brought them home.
Ever since she was a little girl,
she couldn't leave a stray abandoned.
Before these troubles began...
...was Emily a happy girl?
Oh, yes.
Before she went away
to university...
...my Emily was so very happy.
What is going on..? Girls!
Mama.
Is it..?
It's a scholarship, Mama.
They pay for it.
They pay for everything.
This is your dream, Emily.
You'll be leaving us.
It's okay.
I'll be okay.
I'm gonna show this to your father.
- Counselor. Thanks for meeting me.
- Sure.
Can I buy you a drink, Mr. Thomas?
He makes an excellent martini.
Just water for me, please.
So...
...the judge thinks we should offer
a new plea agreement.
She feels the community might be
better served without this trial.
How do you feel about it?
Personally.
My job is to represent
the interests of the people...
...and make an effort to be objective.
I ask because I know
you're a churchgoer.
Now you're set to prosecute
a man of God.
Your priest broke the law...
...and a young girl is dead.
If he's a man of God, then, personally,
I think he's even more subject...
...to the laws of moral behavior.
If it were up to me, he'd get no deal.
And forgiveness and compassion?
Isn't that part of your creed?
Or does that just get in the way
of your work?
If you have compassion
for your client...
...you'll persuade him to accept this:
Charges reduced
to reckless endangerment.
Twelve months in a county jail.
Reducible to six, plus probation,
if he stays out of trouble.
Somehow I expect
he can manage that.
But please understand me.
If he refuses, I will seek the maximum.
Father Moore has made it clear
there will be no plea agreement.
He will not lie or admit to something
he is not guilty of.
- And he was never neglectful of Emily.
- "Never neglectful"?
Have you seen
the postmortem photographs?
We'll go to trial. My client wants
the public to know the truth.
Good.
So do I.
Have a good night, counselor.
Let the record show that the defendant
and his counsel are present...
...and that the jury is seated.
- Mr. Thomas, you may begin.
- Thank you, Your Honor.
Good morning, ladies and gentlemen.
My name is Ethan Thomas.
I'm the assistant district attorney,
and I represent the people.
In the case before you,
the evidence will show...
...that the victim had a serious medical
condition that demanded treatment.
We will prove that the victim's
condition rendered her physically...
...and psychologically incapable
of caring for herself.
Her care...
...was then wholly entrusted...
...to that man, the defendant,
Father Richard Moore.
She became his responsibility...
...and he betrayed
that responsibility...
...by persuading her to abandon
her medical treatment...
...in favor of religious treatment:
A ritual exorcism,
performed by the defendant...
...allegedly to cure the victim
by ridding her of demonic forces.
We will demonstrate
that this course of action...
...directly resulted
in the victim's death.
I said a moment ago
that I represent the people.
We all know what that means,
but it's a little abstract, isn't it?
Miss Bruner,
the attorney for the defense...
...is seated right next
to the man she represents.
And I stand here
to represent the people.
That's not really why
I stand here today.
I'm here on behalf of someone
who can't sit at a table...
...and look at you every day
and gain your sympathy...
...someone who can't take the stand
to testify...
...and tell you what happened
in her own words.
A young girl...
...that could've been your daughter.
Could've been mine.
A girl who trusted
Father Richard Moore with her life.
This is what she looked like...
...before the defendant began
his religious treatment.
This is a photograph taken of her
on the day that she died.
I stand here for Emily Rose...
...who died horribly...
...at age 19.
You won't be able to see Emily sitting
here day after day during this trial.
But I hope you'll remember her
as she was when she was alive...
...and full of...
...hopes and dreams.
And as she was when Father
Richard Moore was finished with her...
...and left her to die.
Thank you.
Is the defense prepared
to make its opening statement?
I'd like to reserve
my opening statement...
...until the presentation
of the defense's case.
As is your privilege.
Prosecution may begin.
That was already my plan.
Thank you, Your Honor.
The people call Dr. Edith Vogel.
I've known Emily her entire life.
I took care of all of the Rose girls.
Can you describe Emily
as you knew her growing up?
She was a bit sickly
in her early years.
She stayed inside a lot,
reading, learning music.
How did she feel about
going to school?
Objection.
The witness is not a psychiatrist.
I'll rephrase. Did you talk to Emily
about going off to college?
Yes. She told me she was excited...
...but nervous that she would be away
from her family in the big city.
This was an overwhelming change
for her.
Did you stay in touch
after she went away?
Yes. She wrote me a letter
saying that she'd been to a dance...
...and she'd met a boy
named Jason.
She didn't want her mother
to know this...
...because her mother did not
approve of dancing...
...and had warned her
about the boys at school.
Did Emily communicate with you again
last fall after you received the letter?
Actually, it was her mother.
She telephoned me...
...waking me out of a deep sleep
at 4 in the morning.
She asked me to call Emily at
a payphone on the university campus.
When Emily answered,
she was quite hysterical.
At first, she just
sobbed uncontrollably.
But eventually she calmed down
enough to tell me what happened.
She said that she was alone
that weekend.
Her roommate had gone home.
She had awakened...
... and thought she smelled
something burning.
There was no alarm,
but she got up...
... afraid there was a fire.
Dr. Mueller, what's your position
at the university hospital?
I am chairman of
the Department of Neurology.
And after you heard
about the dorm-room incident...
...what were your initial thoughts?
At first, I thought perhaps
Emily had taken illegal drugs.
Some type of hallucinogen.
But we ran tests and found no trace
of drugs in her system.
And the more she explained
the incident to me...
...the more I began to suspect
something else.
Epilepsy results from uncontrolled
electrical activity in the brain.
In a severe, or grand mal, seizure...
... a person may lose consciousness
for several minutes...
... and suffer involuntary contractions
of all the muscles of the body.
Is it possible for a person
suffering such a seizure...
... to have hallucinations or perceive
the things that Emily described?
The muscle contractions could feel
like an extreme pressure on the body.
And it is certainly possible,
with all that brain activity...
...for a person to perceive all sorts
of strange and violent things.
So suspecting that Emily was
epileptic, how did you proceed?
I administered
an electroencephalograph.
What did the EEG reveal?
It showed a possible epileptic focus
in the patient's left temporal lobe.
Did this require
a specific treatment?
Yes, I began a medication schedule
for Emily with the drug Gambutrol.
I also advised regular follow-up
examinations and further tests.
But Emily failed to keep
her follow-up appointments with me.
She give any reason for discontinuing
these appointments?
Yes, she told me she was convinced
that her condition was a spiritual one.
It was the conviction of her priest,
she said, and she shared his beliefs.
Was it your impression
that Emily had placed her care...
...entirely..?
- Leading the witness.
Sustained.
After the end of October...
...did you ask Emily
why she had stopped...
...filling her Gambutrol
prescriptions?
Yes. She said that Father Moore had
suggested she stop taking the drug.
And what, in your medical opinion...
...was the result
of Father Moore's suggestion?
I believe Father Moore's suggestion
killed her.
Objection, Your Honor!
The witness is asserting outrageous
conclusions based on pure hearsay.
Technically correct, but I'll allow it
as part of his expert opinion testimony.
Thank you, Dr. Mueller.
Your witness.
You said you observed a possible
epileptic focus in the temporal lobe.
Doesn't this imply what you observed
may not have been an epileptic focus?
Yes, that's also possible.
Would Father Moore's advice to stop
taking Gambutrol be good advice...
...if Emily were, in fact,
not epileptic?
Of course. But that's not
the case here. She was epileptic.
Really.
When Emily saw objects move
on their own...
...and felt an invisible presence
on top of her...
...was she experiencing symptoms
typical of epilepsy?
Not typical, no.
Are they typical indications
of any other conditions?
- Say, for example, psychosis?
- Yes, I would say that's correct.
But isn't psychosis an entirely different
medical condition from epilepsy?
- Yes, in my...
- So aren't you selectively choosing...
...what parts of Emily's experiences
fit your epilepsy diagnosis...
...while ignoring those which
indicate something else?
- Objection. Argumentative.
- Withdrawn.
No further questions.
We have to work fast.
They're only giving me an hour
with you tonight.
Listen.
Before we get started,
there's something I have to tell you...
...something I should've said to you
before I let you take the case.
Okay.
There are forces
surrounding this trial.
Dark, powerful forces.
Just be careful, Erin.
Watch your step.
I see.
Look...
Father, you don't have to worry
about me.
I'm an agnostic, remember?
Demons exist,
whether you believe in them or not.
Your involvement in this trial might
just open you up to their attacks.
Look, Father,
I appreciate your concern...
...but you need to be worried
about yourself.
Ethan Thomas is using the medical
aspects of this case as ammunition...
...and I have to be prepared
for his attacks, so...
...with what little time we have, I think
we need to focus on your defense.
Now, what I need from you is more
information about Emily's condition.
Specific details of how it progressed
after the dorm-room episode.
Well, after the first incident...
...she was sent to the university
hospital for testing and observation.
Emily once told me that in her
dorm room, she resisted the demons...
...but at the hospital
they overcame her.
So she believed...
...that her possession
began at the hospital?
Yeah, I think she did.
And after that, things just went
from bad to worse.
Emily!
Emily?
Oh, my God. Emily?
Don't touch me.
Jason, please...
...don't leave me.
And I never did leave her.
I stayed until the end.
So much of what we shared
was like a nightmare...
...but I wouldn't give up
a single minute I spent with her.
She woke me up, you know?
To things I never felt before,
things I never knew I could feel.
I never knew how dead I was
until I met her.
- residential north metro district
where James Van Hopper...
... acquitted after
a controversial trial...
- Can you turn that up, please?
- ... has apparently struck again.
It was inside
this quiet suburban home...
... that police say James Van Hopper
murdered a young couple today.
Sources close to the investigation
say that Van Hopper...
... who was acquitted
of murder charges in April...
... may have known
both of the victims.
Their names are being withheld
pending family notification.
Most glorious prince
of the heavenly army...
...holy Michael, the archangel...
...defend us in battle
against the princes...
...powers and rulers of darkness.
Counsel Bruner, my courtroom day
begins at 9:30 a. m.
- I'm sorry, Your Honor, I...
- Which was 17 minutes ago.
Ready to proceed?
Yes, Your Honor.
Dr. Briggs, please state
your qualifications for the court.
I have advanced degrees
in medicine...
...psychiatry and neurology
from Johns Hopkins...
...and I have had three books
and several dozen papers published...
...in the fields of neurology
and neuropsychiatry.
What was the cause of death,
as determined by the autopsy?
The decedent expired due to a gradual
shutdown of the bodily functions.
Why did her body shut down?
The autopsy found
that it was a cumulative effect...
...from numerous physical traumas
exacerbated by malnutrition...
...which severely inhibited her ability
to recuperate from those traumas.
In other words, her starving body
had little or no means to recover...
...from the injuries it was sustaining,
and so it eventually just gave out.
How did Emily get these injuries?
Some were the result
of violent epileptic seizures...
...and some were self-inflicted.
And why, in your opinion,
did Emily injure herself...
...and why did she stop eating?
Upon review
of her complete medical file...
...I concluded that Emily's epilepsy
had evolved...
...into a condition known as
psychotic epileptic disorder.
This is a rare development,
to be sure...
...but one that I have witnessed
numerous times.
- Emily was epileptic and psychotic?
- Yes.
Explain how this psychotic epileptic
disorder would manifest itself.
The seizures would have
the symptoms of schizophrenia...
... such as auditory
and visual hallucinations...
... and sometimes extreme paranoia.
The seizures may lock up the joints
and slightly contort the body.
The pupils will dilate,
making the eyes appear black.
So you believe
that Emily had epilepsy...
...which developed into
a form of violent psychosis...
...a condition that can be controlled
with Gambutrol?
Yes. And it would've been,
if she'd continued her treatment.
In your opinion, if Emily
had continued with her medication...
...would she be alive today?
- Absolutely.
If treated early, psychotic epileptic
disorder is rarely fatal.
I mean, this...
This was a very sick girl.
The defendant should've realized
that Emily was in need...
...of continued medical treatment.
Thank you, doctor. Your witness.
Doctor, you testified that Gambutrol
could've controlled Emily's condition.
How do you know that?
It's the inevitable result
of taking the drug.
It would've controlled
her seizures...
...which were the root cause
of her psychosis.
But wasn't Emily still experiencing
psychotic symptoms...
...even after she started
taking the medication?
Yes. Because Gambutrol
has a cumulative effect.
It takes time to build up
in the system.
You assume that Gambutrol would've
helped her, but you don't know.
It's a reasonable assumption, but...
No, of course, I can't be certain.
Doctor, is "psychotic epileptic
disorder" a common medical term...
...or did you just make it up?
Well, I distinguished
and named the...
So psychotic epileptic disorder
is really your own pet theory?
- Objection. Argumentative.
- Sustained.
When Emily chose
to stop her medical treatment...
...what do you think
should've been done?
Upon recognizing her condition...
...I would have tranquilized her
and force-fed her.
And then, if necessary...
...I would've treated her
with electroconvulsive therapy.
Electroshock treatment. You would've
done this against her will?
To save her life?
Absolutely.
Nothing further.
The witness may step down.
Your Honor, I offer into evidence this
photograph as People's Exhibit 3-A.
And having done so,
the people rest.
The photograph is entered
into evidence.
We are recessed until
tomorrow morning, 9:30 sharp...
...at which time the defense
will give its opening statement...
...and call its first witness.
I'm sorry I was late.
I didn't get a lot of sleep. Big power
outage knocked out my alarm clock.
- It won't happen again.
- No, I didn't sleep either.
What kept you awake?
Doesn't matter.
You're under attack.
What are you talking about?
You're in a spiritual battle, Erin.
The forces of darkness are trying
to keep you away from the light.
Don't let them.
Don't worry about today.
We're doing fine.
We're getting creamed.
I can't believe I walked right into that.
Look, if we don't find a doctor
to testify that Emily...
...wasn't epileptic or schizophrenic
or schizo-epileptic, we're gonna lose.
Care of the city's main branch
and the university library...
...I bring you another dozen
fun-filled books...
...about the demonic
and the mentally deranged.
They burned women at the stake...
...during witch hunts
for being possessed.
Glad you don't have to defend
those guys.
- How are we on our medical experts?
- Not good.
The psychiatrist you wanted
is tied up in another trial.
And the neurologist is sailing
to Costa Rica.
This book I'm reading,
it's by an anthropologist.
It's about contemporary cases of
possession, mostly in the Third World.
People there are still
primitive and superstitious.
Maybe.
Maybe they see possession
for what it really is.
Maybe we've taught ourselves
not to see it.
- You saying you believe in this stuff?
- No.
Maybe we shouldn't just try
to invalidate the prosecution's case...
...by punching holes
in the medical approach.
Maybe we should also try
to validate the alternative.
- Validate possession in a court of law?
- Yes.
Okay. I guess we could bring in
some priests to talk about exorcisms...
No, the archdiocese
won't let us do that.
They wanna limit the Church's
exposure to Father Moore.
I've got three articles by the
anthropologist who wrote this book.
She approaches
the subject of possession...
...from a scientific perspective
and doesn't try to debunk it.
- You want me to track her down?
- Yeah.
Keep looking for a medical expert
to refute Dr. Briggs.
But send the case file
to this Dr. Sadira Adani.
Ladies and gentlemen of the jury...
...as you know by now,
my name is Erin Bruner...
...and I represent the defendant,
Richard Moore.
Mr. Thomas has contended
that Emily Rose suffered...
...from a serious medical condition...
...that required medical treatment,
nothing more.
He has asserted that any attempt
by my client...
...to help Emily by anything
other than medical means...
...was not only inappropriate,
but criminally negligent.
I'm now gonna ask
that you keep an open mind...
...to what our evidence
and testimony will show.
Medical treatment was not
the answer for Emily...
...because she simply did not suffer
from a medical condition.
She was neither epileptic
nor psychotic.
Emily Rose's condition, in fact,
was demonic possession.
An exorcism was her only hope
for a cure.
Some of you may find yourself unable
to reconcile Emily's beliefs...
...or those of the defendant
with your own.
You may not believe demons exist.
You won't have to.
Because you will see that after the
utter failure of doctors to help Emily...
...Father Moore simply tried
to help Emily in a different way...
...using an approach that he,
Emily and her family firmly believed...
...was her only chance for relief.
And we will show that
despite his greatest efforts...
...and his sincere love for Emily...
... there was nothing he could've done
to prevent the death of Emily Rose.
Are you okay?
Aren't you gonna eat anything?
She said it was terrible to hear
the clinking of spoons and forks.
She was always hungry,
but she said they wouldn't let her eat.
Who did she mean by "they"?
The forces that were
in control of her.
That were inside her.
You know, the demons.
Tell us what else happened
that night.
I walked her back to her dorm...
...and she seemed really nervous
and scared.
So I held her for a while,
trying to calm her down.
I fell asleep, but when I woke up,
she wasn't beside me.
Emily?
Hey.
Can you hear me?
I called her father, and he told me
to bring Emily home.
Jason and I put Emily to bed...
... hoping she would sleep.
And when did Father Moore
become involved?
Emily stayed home after that.
She didn't return to school,
and she kept getting worse.
Eventually, when she didn't get better,
we called our priest, Father Moore.
When he arrived,
I sent my daughter Alice upstairs...
... to see if Emily was awake.
Emily?
Can I come in?
- Our Father, who art in heaven...
- Emily?
Father Moore is here.
Can you come downstairs?
- as it is in heaven.
Give us this day our daily bread...
Emily, can you hear me?
Let's get her off the floor.
Alice, no!
Ego sum qui intus habitat.
(I am the one that dwells within)
Et ego sum qui venit in nomine eius.
(And I am the one who comes  in His name!)
Num putas me expellere, sacerdos?
(You really think you can cast me out, priest?)
Tente.
(Try.)
Ego te provoco.
(I dare you.)
You've suffered a terrible loss,
Mr. Rose. I know this is difficult.
So thank you for being here today.
Sir, do you often read the Bible?
- Yes, I do.
- So do I.
What about the DSM?
The Diagnostic and Statistical
Manual of Mental Disorders...
...commonly referred to
as the bible of abnormal psychiatry.
- Have you read that?
- No.
So you're not aware
that according to the DSM...
...a person's refusal to eat is
a common indication of anorexia?
Objection. The witness just said
he hasn't read the DSM, Your Honor.
- Sustained.
- Mr. Rose...
...are you aware
that catatonic rigidity...
...specifically a locking up
of the body's joints...
...is a known symptom of psychosis?
No. I haven't studied these things.
Have you ever visited
an insane asylum...
...or a hospital for the mentally ill?
Once. My aunt was in one
before she died.
Really? So there's a history
of mental illness in your family?
I suppose.
Sir, if you saw someone
eating insects...
...on a street corner, would you say
that that person is mentally ill?
- Probably, yes.
- So can you say with confidence...
...that the behavior you saw
in your daughter's bedroom...
...could not be the behavior of
someone suffering from psychosis?
I don't know. She never had
any problems like that before.
It just didn't feel that way to me
or to Father Moore.
- And you trusted him, right?
- Yes.
He is our parish priest.
Fair enough. And after that night,
would you say that you...
...put your daughter entirely
in Father Moore's care?
Yes. We had done all we could.
We said she was in his hands now...
...body and soul.
Thank you. No further questions,
Your Honor.
Thank you, Mr. Rose.
You may step down.
The defense calls Dr. Sadira Adani.
I am currently a professor
of anthropology and psychiatry...
...at Northwestern University.
Where did you receive
your education?
At Yale, and then at Cambridge.
And what is your specific area
of expertise?
I study the spiritual experiences
of people in various cultures...
...and the physiological
and psychological changes...
...they undergo
during these experiences.
Would it be accurate to say that you
specialize in the study of possession?
Yes. "Possession" is one term
for a basic human experience...
...reported by a great number
of people all around the world.
In my fieldwork, I've seen
many people who experienced...
...a sense of being invaded by
an entity from the supernatural realm.
Why do you think
Emily was invaded?
Why did this possession
happen to her?
Based on my study of the case file...
...I believe that Emily Rose
was a hypersensitive.
A person with
an unusual connection...
...to what Carlos Castaneda called
"the separate reality."
Hypersensitives are born
different from everyone else.
They can have visions of the future,
or see the dead...
...and sometimes be
uniquely susceptible...
...to invasion by an entity
that is alien to them.
Objection.
On what grounds?
How about silliness, Your Honor?
A young girl
suffered terribly and died.
Do we have to subject her illness
to this pseudoscientific analysis?
Both counselors,
please approach the bench.
Your Honor, this testimony
is beyond ridiculous. Visions...
Supernatural belief systems
are shared by millions of people.
We're in The Twilight Zone here.
Her expertise is relevant
to the issues in this case.
Let's have a witch doctor
sift through bones...
Stop.
We've heard a great deal
of testimony...
...in support of a medical explanation
for Emily's condition.
Now we have a witness
who has spent her career...
...studying the defense's
alternative explanation.
An exorcism expert, if you will.
I think we'll hear
what she has to say.
Thank you, Your Honor.
Dr. Adani, why do you think
Emily's exorcism failed?
The medical treatment.
Specifically, the drug Gambutrol.
Please explain.
The exorcism ritual results
in a specific brain activity...
...that cuts the person off from
the possession experience.
But Emily's exorcism
could not have achieved this...
...because the doctor
gave her Gambutrol...
...which has an intoxicating effect
on the brain.
The drug made her immune
to the psycho-spiritual shock...
...that exorcism
is intended to provide.
What do you believe was the result of
treatment with this intoxicating drug?
Gambutrol locked Emily
in the possessed state.
This left her unable to respond
to the exorcism...
...and therefore, it directly
contributed to her death.
Thank you, doctor.
No further questions.
I'm looking at a list of
your published articles, doctor.
You've been quite busy and prolific.
So based on your time spent
with Holy Roller snake-handlers...
...voodoo priestesses
and Indians tripping on peyote buds...
...based on observing
these bizarre individuals...
...you've concluded
that possession is...
...a basic, typical
human experience?
I must say, counselor...
...that's quite a laundry list
of disdain...
...and one that thoroughly
mischaracterizes my research.
No, I don't think possession
is a typical experience.
But I am convinced that it is
a scientifically verified...
...culturally universal one.
Have you ever used Gambutrol
in your studies...
...to test your theory about its effect
on the possession experience?
Absolutely not. That would be
dangerous to the patient.
So this notion of Gambutrol locking
someone in a possessed state...
...the key to your assertion that
her medical treatment harmed Emily...
...this would be your own
pet theory, correct?
- You're just making this one up?
- Objection. Argumentative.
Sustained.
Although I think he's just taking
a page from your book, counselor.
No further questions.
Erin!
I've got a doctor
who wants to testify.
He's an eyewitness, Erin.
He was there.
He was at the exorcism.
- What?
- He called us.
Dr. Graham Cartwright,
Department of Abnormal Psychiatry...
...at St. Mary's Hospital.
Dr. Cartwright. Ring a bell?
Yes.
He was there?
- Yes.
- Father...
...if you want me to defend you,
you've got to give me...
...all the information I need.
With all of this medical testimony
helping the prosecution...
...how could you not tell me
that a doctor attended the exorcism?
He asked that I keep
his involvement confidential...
...and I said I would.
Dr. Cartwright?
I recognize you from those
courtroom drawings on the news.
You're much prettier in real life.
- May I sit?
- Yes, please.
You're losing.
I had hoped Father Moore
wouldn't need me...
...but I don't wanna see him
put away.
How do you know him?
Well, I was his parishioner
at St. Vincent's Church...
...about 15 years ago.
I hadn't seen or heard of him for years
when he called me last fall.
But he needed help, so...
What kind of help, doctor?
He wanted a medical perspective
from a psychiatrist...
...you know, one that he knew,
trusted...
...to observe Emily's physical
and mental state during this...
During the exorcism.
Yeah.
Doctor.
Can you help our case?
That girl was not schizophrenic...
...and she was not epileptic,
or any combination of the two.
I've seen hundreds of people
with those problems.
They can be terrible afflictions,
of course, but they don't scare me.
But what you saw that night in Emily,
that did scare you.
God, if I'd known,
I never would've been there.
I started praying again
since then, you know.
I examined that girl before I drove
back to the city that night.
She was lucid...
...and she was completely aware
of this separate entity inside her.
When she wasn't in his grip, she was
totally herself, completely normal.
The awareness of her alternate mental
state is counterindicative of psychosis.
Crazy people
don't know they're crazy.
That's right.
You'll testify to all of this, in detail?
Everything you saw?
Send me the case files
and tell me when to be in court.
Thank you, doctor.
We need this.
Before he was arrested,
Father Moore sent this to me.
He asked me to take care of it.
It's your burden now.
One more thing.
When you saw Emily...
...did Father Moore ask you
to give her any medical help?
He was already trying to stop her from
injuring herself and urging her to eat.
And I told him, as a doctor,
I couldn't help her.
Dr. Cartwright's going to testify.
Don't you get it?
He's not just an eyewitness
to the exorcism.
He can also refute the prosecution's
medical case. This is huge for us.
When do I get to testify?
I don't know. Let's take this
one step at a time.
No.
What matters most is Emily's story,
which only I can tell.
I understand.
Have you thought about
what I said before?
About dark forces
and demonic attacks?
Yes, I have.
That day, after Briggs testified...
... I was feeling awful.
And I went out for a walk
just to clear my head...
... and I was thinking about
what you said to me. Thinking:
"What if demons really do exist?"
And wondering what that
would mean if I believed that.
Because God knows,
I have my own demons.
And I saw something
lying on the sidewalk.
It was a gold locket...
... with the initials E. C.B.
engraved on it.
My middle name is Christine.
Erin Christine Bruner.
And of all the people walking by
that day, I found that locket.
What are the chances of that?
I don't know, maybe it was a sign.
Or maybe it was just some
incredible coincidence.
But it made me feel...
...like no matter what mistakes
I've made in the past...
...at that moment, I was exactly
where I was meant to be.
Like I was on the right path.
You sound more like a mystic
than an agnostic.
Are you wearing the locket now?
No.
You should.
The archdiocese
doesn't want you to testify.
They're just afraid
that I'll embarrass them.
Testify to some medieval-sounding
supernatural nonsense.
They're expecting me
to talk you out of it.
I've just decided
I'm not even gonna try.
Why not?
If the archdiocese
wants to avoid embarrassment...
...they need you to walk out of here
a free man.
I believe a jury will find you
sincere and credible...
...and when Dr. Cartwright
corroborates your testimony...
...and refutes the prosecution's
medical arguments...
...we'll get an acquittal.
And everyone will thank me for it.
Emily!
God help me.
Do you swear to tell the truth,
the whole truth, so help you God?
I do.
Father Moore, before you could
perform the exorcism...
...you had to get the sanction
of the Church, correct?
Yes, on October the 27th
of last year...
...I presented my assessment and
recommendation to the archbishop...
...and he authorized the exorcism
that day before I left the office.
Tell us what happened that night.
I drove home.
I sat up till after midnight
studying The Roman Ritual...
...thinking about what lay ahead.
You mean The Roman Ritual
of Exorcism.
A text used by Catholic priests...
...as a guide to performing
the exorcism rite.
Yes, I think I actually fell asleep
with the book in my hand.
What happened next?
I woke up, freezing.
It was exactly 3 a. m.
Three a. m. is the demonic
witching hour.
It's a way for demons
to mock the Holy Trinity.
It's an inversion of 3 p. m.,
the miracle hour...
...which is traditionally accepted
as the hour of Christ's death.
I thought I smelled
something burning.
Only later did I connect it...
... and I remembered that that same
smell of something burning...
... had been perceived by Emily.
Holy Mary, mother of God,
pray for us sinners, now and...
Pray for us sinners,
now and at the hour of our...
At the hour of...
What do you make of this gesture,
this nod in your direction?
I don't know. Some kind
of acknowledgment, I guess.
That the game is on.
You're really God's gunslinger,
aren't you, Father?
Standing tall and facing the devil
with your prayer book at your side.
Objection, Your Honor.
Counsel's harassing my witness.
Sustained. Mr. Thomas, you know
I won't allow that in my courtroom.
Forgive me, Your Honor.
Father, did you understand this
black-robed figure to be the devil?
I believe it was
a demonic manifestation.
Like the demonic force
you believe possessed Emily?
- Yes.
- Why do you think it appeared to you?
I believe the demonic
can appear as an apparition...
...much like a ghost,
in an attempt to excite our fear.
- Did it excite your fear, Father?
- It scared the hell out of me.
So this night, when you began to
prepare Emily's exorcism...
...was it your first encounter
with this demon ghost?
- Yes.
- Have you seen it again?
I've seen it ever since.
No further questions at this time.
Redirect, Your Honor.
Father Moore, after you received
the bishop's authorization...
...when did you proceed
with an exorcism?
October 31st.
On Halloween.
Isn't that a bit dramatic?
Halloween tradition is based on
legends throughout history...
...that indicate a real increase
in spiritual activity on that night...
...and I thought we could use the
occasion to draw them into the open.
- The demons, you mean?
- Yes.
Father Moore...
...can you identify this?
It's my tape recorder.
I used it to record the exorcism.
Inside is the tape I made that night.
Why would you make such a tape?
Ever since the technology
has been available...
...exorcists have used tape recorders
to authenticate the ritual...
...and provide a record for review.
I offer into evidence this
cassette recorder and audiotape...
Objection. The people were not aware
of the existence of this tape...
...until last night.
- Neither were we.
This tape is new evidence that came
into our possession yesterday.
We provided counsel for the people
with a transcript of its contents.
You mean this tape was not
given to you by your client?
No, Your Honor. We received it
from a reluctant witness...
...Dr. Graham Cartwright, who will also
be called to testify to its authenticity.
The people will find his name
on the updated witness list...
...we provided to them this morning.
Very well. I'll allow it into evidence.
Father Moore.
Will you play the tape for us now?
This is the exorcism of Emily Rose.
Those present are myself,
Father Richard Moore...
...Nathaniel, Emily's father...
...Jason, her friend...
...a doctor who is here
to monitor Emily during the ritual...
...and Emily herself...
...who has given her permission
for the ritual to be performed.
All right, now listen.
You may say the rosary or any
private prayer for her deliverance...
...when you're not responding
to my words.
Above all...
...do whatever I ask,
without question.
Don't ask it any questions...
...or pay any attention
to what it says.
"It"?
We won't be dealing
with Emily tonight.
Restrain her.
Lord Jesus Christ,
have mercy on us.
It has begun.
Let us pray.
"Because she hopes
in you, my God."
"Send her help from
the holy place, Lord."
"And give her heavenly protection."
"May the Lord be with you."
"And with your spirit."
Our Father, who art in heaven,
hallowed be thy name.
My God. Are you all right?
Ein Kuss ein Kreuz und Bitten?
(A kiss, a cross and wishes? )
Glaubst du etwa, das wird dein kleines Mädchen retten?
(You really think that will save your little girl?)
Thy kingdom come, thy will be done,
on earth as it is in heaven.
I'm fine.
Give us this day our daily bread.
And forgive us our trespasses as we
forgive those that trespass against us.
And lead us not into temptation...
But deliver us from evil!
Who are you, demon?
Tell me your name.
Ego sum qui intus habitat...
(I am the one who dwells within...)
In nomine christi...
(In the name of Christ...)
...designate!
(...identify yourself!)
One, two, three, four, five, six.
Trick or treat.
I give you treats and tricks.
One, two, three, four, five, six.
Father Moore!
Papa!
Emily!
She feels so hot, Father!
She's burning up!
Hold her down there on the straw!
Hold her!
Emily!
Doctor! I need you here now.
Watch her vital signs.
In the beginning was the word.
And the word was with God.
And the word was the word,
and what a wonderful word it was.
Through him all things remain.
Without him, nothing was made
that has been made.
And the 70 disciples
returned again with joy, saying:
"Lord, even the devils are subject
unto us through thy name."
Her heart is racing.
It's almost 180 beats a minute.
I beheld Satan as lightning
fall from heaven.
Behold. I give you power to tread on
serpents and scorpions...
...and over all the power
of the enemy.
And nothing shall,
by any means, hurt you.
Ouden?
( Nothing? )
Get it off! Get it off! Get it off!
Release him, demon. I command you
in the name of our Lord, Jesus Christ.
Tell me your name, wicked one.
He who commands you is he
who ordered you thrown down...
...from the highest heaven
into the depths of hell.
In the name of our Lord, Jesus Christ,
I now command you:
Tell me your name!
Eins, zwei, drei, vier, fünf, sechs!
(One, two, three, four, five, six!)
Hear, therefore, and fear,
Satan, enemy of the faith.
Give me your name, demon!
Names!
One, two, three, four, five, six!
Ancient serpents...
...depart from this servant of God!
Tell me your six names!
We are the ones who dwell within!
I am the one who dwelt within Cain!
I am the one who dwelt within Nero!
I once dwelt within Judas!
And I was with Legion!
I am Belial!
And I am Lucifer...
...the devil in the flesh.
Mr. Rose.
Doctor, help him!
After a few moments,
Mr. Rose revived...
... but the exorcism
had to be abandoned.
Emily was taken to her room
and soon fell into a deep sleep.
The whole thing
was a complete failure.
Describe her behavior from the night
of the failed exorcism...
...until the time of her death.
Violence towards others and herself.
Sometimes she screamed
for hours on end.
She drove her head through windows,
tried to bite...
Tried to bite holes in the walls,
breaking several more of her teeth...
...as you saw in
the postmortem photograph.
- You witnessed this?
- Some of it, yes.
I tried to visit every day...
...and the family told me the rest.
Did you attempt another exorcism?
I wanted to, but Emily refused.
And without the consent
of the possessed...
...the exorcism ritual
can't be performed.
Did you encourage her to eat?
Yes, every time I saw her...
...but the few times she tried,
it seemed like...
Seemed like she couldn't swallow,
or she couldn't keep it down.
What about medical care?
I wanted her to continue. I never said
she should quit seeing her doctors.
That would be wrong.
Medical care is not my field.
But you did suggest she stop
taking the drug Gambutrol.
Yes.
After the exorcism,
she asked for my counsel.
She told me that the drugs
had never helped her.
After all, she was on Gambutrol
during the exorcism...
...when her so-called symptoms
were at their peak.
Ultimately, we both felt that
she was beyond medical care...
...and that she had to see this
through to the end...
...by faith alone.
The dual voices we just heard
on this tape...
...you're certain that they were both
coming from Emily at the same time?
Yes. Yes, I heard them.
Have you tampered
with this tape in any way?
No. No, I have not.
No further questions at this time.
Mr. Thomas.
Father Moore, you consider this tape
to be proof of the supernatural?
I think it's a record
of certain indications...
...that Emily was possessed.
Signs of possession,
you may call them.
By "signs of possession," would you
mean her speaking in languages...
...we might assume
she couldn't possibly know?
And the vocalization of two
distinct voices simultaneously?
Yes. Among other signs that I
observed and described to the court...
...while the tape was playing.
Things I saw.
Things you can't hear
on the tape.
We'll just have to take
your word, won't we?
- Your Honor.
- Mr. Thomas.
I apologize.
Father, as Emily's parish priest...
...are you aware that she underwent
advanced catechism training?
Yes. Yes. Her family is very devout.
And in that training, did she study
Ancient Greek, Hebrew and Latin?
Yes, I think that's right.
Might have even studied Aramaic,
Christ and his disciples' language...
...which, according to the transcripts,
we also heard on the tape, correct?
She spoke Aramaic on the tape.
It wasn't part of her training.
But it was offered as an elective
at her catechism school.
I have the school's curriculum
here if you'd like to see it.
No. I'll accept that she might have
been exposed to that language.
And according to
her high school records...
...German was the foreign language
she studied there, yes?
I don't know. If you say so.
So that covers the strange languages
we heard on the tape, correct?
Did I miss any?
- No.
- Good.
We've already established
you're no medical expert.
You said it's not your field.
But are you aware of the dual sets of
vocal cords every human possesses?
- No.
- Have you heard of...
...the superior vocal cords, which are
higher than the ones we use to speak?
No. So you didn't know that
Tibetan monks, for example...
...as part of their religious training,
teach themselves...
...to activate both sets
of vocal cords at once?
No, I didn't know that.
Well, now that you do know,
would you think it's possible...
...that Emily, in her psychotic state...
...might have activated both sets
of vocal cords...
...so as to achieve the amazing effect
we heard captured on your audiotape?
Her state was not psychotic.
Father Moore, you told us
that in the exorcism we heard...
...you actually saw, once again,
this black-robed figure...
...or demonic apparition, am I right?
- Yes.
But we couldn't see him
when you played the tape, correct?
- No, of course not.
- Of course not.
So that would be another
supernatural aspect of the exorcism...
...your tape doesn't prove, correct?
- Yes.
Where is your dark figure, Father?
Is he here now?
Do I look like your demon ghost?
- Your Honor.
- Counselor.
I have nothing further.
Does the defense wish to redirect?
No, Your Honor, but we reserve
the right to recall the witness later.
Very well.
The witness may step down.
Your Honor, my next witness
must have been detained.
If we could take a short recess
so I could...
You've made this court wait before,
counselor. I'm inclined to...
Your Honor, please.
Dr. Cartwright came to us
in good conscience...
...as an eyewitness to the exorcism
on Father Moore's tape.
He can substantiate
all of my client's testimony...
Your Honor, the defense has already
presented its exorcism testimony...
...in dramatic fashion.
Do we really have to..?
We have absorbed some
extraordinary testimony today.
I think we'll take some time
to consider it.
Court is adjourned
until 9:30 tomorrow morning.
- You can't find him?
- I went to meet him, he didn't show.
I called his office, I called his house.
Okay. Go to the hospital, ask around.
Somebody's gotta know where he is.
What the hell happened?
Tell Father Moore I'm sorry.
Tell him I know the demons are real
and I admire his courage...
...for standing and speaking
against them.
Tell him I know what they can do.
- Cartwright's dead.
- I heard.
Are you drunk?
- Not yet, but I'm working on it.
- Have you seen this?
- What the hell were you thinking?
- Karl...
You told me you'd talk him out
of testifying.
Instead, you put on a freak show
with taped demons...
...and a dead girl
speaking in tongues...
...and your client testifies that the
archbishop sanctioned the exorcism.
We'll be lucky if
the archdiocese isn't named...
I had a doctor
who was gonna corroborate.
Besides that, Father Moore's
testimony's crucial to his defense.
Did you forget the archdiocese
is paying for this defense?
The archdiocese isn't on trial.
I swore an oath to do
what's best for my client.
Spare me the law school pieties,
Bruner.
You cashed in your conscience
at the door.
- People can change.
- Like James Van Hopper?
It's not over.
I can put Mr. Rose on the stand...
...to corroborate Father Moore
about the exorcism.
And there are the girls.
Her sister Alice, she saw part of it.
They all look like superstitious rubes.
They've got no credibility.
Thomas will rip them to pieces.
You'll be worse off than you are now,
if that's possible.
You're gonna replace me
on this case.
You've screwed it up
beyond all repair.
But the archdiocese feels
that replacing you now...
...would only draw more
unnecessary attention to the trial.
But just so we're clear, Bruner...
...if you put that priest
on the stand again, I will fire you.
You've been crying.
- Dr. Cartwright is dead.
- What?
He was killed.
There was an accident. I'm sorry.
I know he was your friend.
We've lost.
Without his testimony, it's over.
No.
No, no, no, it isn't over. We're telling
Emily's story. That's what matters.
- It can't be worth all this.
- Yes, it is worth it.
Just let me go back on the stand
and tell the rest of the story.
- I can't do that.
- You must!
You must.
Erin, you once said that you felt
you were on the right path.
Don't stray from that path.
Here, take this.
- What is this?
- Just read it.
And then decide
what you want to do.
I saw your eyes today in court when
I explained the significance of 3 a. m.
It's not going to stop
until Emily's story is told.
Are you gonna make a statement?
Do you believe it was the devil?
Is the defense ready to proceed?
Yes, Your Honor. The defense
recalls Father Richard Moore.
The witness is reminded
that he is still under oath.
- When did you last see Emily alive?
- The night before she died.
Her mother, Maria, called me
and said that Emily had asked for me.
- Why did she ask to see you?
- To give me this.
Did Emily explain to you
the letter's significance?
Yes. She said she'd written it the
morning after the failed exorcism...
...and that it was important
for me to share.
Father Moore,
was Emily a good person?
I believe that one day
Emily will be recognized as a saint.
- So she loved God.
- Yes. She was very devout.
Father Moore, if Emily loved God...
...if she was so good and so devout,
why do you think God...
...allowed this to happen?
- Objection.
What is the relevance
of that question?
Father Moore's belief
in this matter is crucial...
...in establishing his and Emily's
understanding of her condition.
And that mutual understanding
is paramount in determining...
...whether Father Moore was,
in fact, negligent.
I'm going to allow it.
Your Honor, you're not really gonna
let someone testify...
...about why God would allow
the death of a young girl?
The objection has been overruled.
Again, Father Moore:
Why did God allow Emily to become
possessed by demons and then die?
I can let Emily answer that.
"Last night, on Allhallows' Eve...
...Father Moore tried to cast
six demons from my body.
They refused to go.
After the attempted exorcism..."
I was taken to my room,
and I fell into a deep sleep.
I awoke a few hours later,
hearing a voice calling out my name.
"Again, I heard a voice
calling my name.
It was the Blessed Holy Mother
of God.
And when I looked at her...
...she smiled at me and said:
'Emily, heaven is not blind
to your pain."'
She said the Virgin Mary spoke to her
in the middle of a field?
- Yes.
- And do you believe her?
I believe Emily spoke the truth.
Please continue.
"I asked the Blessed Mother,
'Why do I suffer like this?"'
Why did the demons
not leave me tonight?
"She said, 'I am sorry, Emily.
The demons are going to stay
where they are.'
Then she said,
'You can come with me in peace...
... free of your bodily form...
... or you can choose
to continue this.
You will suffer greatly.
But through you, many will come to
see that the realm of the spirit is real.
The choice is yours."'
I choose to stay.
"In the end,
good will triumph over evil.
Through my experience...
...people will know
that demons are real.
People say that God is dead.
But how can they think that...
...if I show them the devil?"
Did you see these wounds on both
of Emily's hands and both feet?
Yes. Yes, the wounds
lasted for some time.
And did you attach any supernatural
significance to these wounds?
I believe they were stigmata.
By that, you mean
supernatural injuries...
...that correspond to the crucifixion
wounds of Jesus Christ?
Yes.
Stigmata are a sign, a mark
indicating one is touched by God.
After that night, why do you think
Emily refused another exorcism?
I believe she'd accepted her fate.
Is there anything else
you'd like to say about Emily?
No.
The defense rests.
Father Moore attaches
divine significance...
...to the wounds
on Emily's hands and feet.
Why?
Because he sees them as confirmation
of what he wants to believe.
That Emily was a saint,
touched by the hand of God.
I'm afraid the truth
is far less inspiring.
Because the truth is, by the time
these miraculous wounds appeared...
...Emily had already shown
a tendency to injure herself...
...and simply did so again
on one of the barbed-wire fences...
...surrounding the Rose family farm.
Father Moore's beliefs are based on
archaic and irrational superstition.
Emily suffered
because she was sick...
...not because she was a saint.
I'm a man of faith.
And I am also a man of facts.
And in here,
facts are what must matter.
And these are the facts of this case:
Emily Rose had epilepsy,
which caused psychosis.
And, given time,
medicine would have cured her.
But it didn't. Why? Because Father
Richard Moore convinced Emily...
...that she wasn't ill,
that she didn't need medicine.
And in the weeks
leading up to her death...
...when she was clearly in need
of medical treatment...
...he failed to have her hospitalized.
So...
...the defense has given us
an extraordinary...
...creative explanation
for the events that led to this.
Ladies and gentlemen,
don't you believe it.
Because the fact is, it wasn't the devil
that did this to Emily Rose.
It was the defendant.
Counselor.
Ethan Thomas calls himself
a man of faith.
I, on the other hand,
am a woman of doubt.
Angels and demons.
God and the devil.
These things either exist,
or they do not exist.
Are we all alone in this life?
Or are we not alone?
Either thought is astonishing.
Do I really believe that this tragedy
is the work of the devil?
To be honest, I don't know.
But I cannot deny that it's possible.
The prosecution
wants you to believe...
...that Emily's psychotic
epileptic disorder was a fact...
...because facts leave no room
for reasonable doubt.
But this trial isn't about facts.
This trial is about possibilities.
Is it a fact that Emily
was a hypersensitive...
...as Dr. Adani suggests?
A person who's more likely, by her
very nature, to become possessed?
I can't say that, but the question is:
Is it possible?
Is it a fact that Gambutrol
anesthetized Emily's brain...
...so that the exorcism ritual
was rendered ineffective?
I can't be sure of that.
But is it possible?
Is it a fact that Emily
was beloved by God?
And that after her exorcism,
she chose to suffer till the end...
...so that we might believe
in a more magical world?
A world where the spiritual realm
really exists?
I can't say that's a fact.
But ask yourself:
Is it possible?
It's what Emily believed.
It's what Father Moore believed.
And that sincere belief is what
determined her choices and his.
Now, for the most
important question:
Is Father Richard Moore guilty...
...beyond a reasonable doubt,
of negligent homicide?
Did he, in fact, neglect
Emily's needs in such a way...
...that her death
is now on his hands?
No! That is not a fact.
It is not a fact
that Emily was epileptic.
that she was psychotic.
Facts...
...leave no room for possibilities.
The only fact...
...the only thing I know
beyond a doubt in this case...
...is that Father Moore
loved Emily with his whole heart.
He did everything in his power
to help her.
He has risked his very freedom
so we could hear her story.
Ladies and gentlemen of the jury...
...in my job I sometimes
have to defend bad men.
Father Richard Moore
is not one of them.
Don't send a good man to prison.
I'm not asking that you believe
everything that Father Moore believes.
I'm simply asking that you believe
in Father Moore.
Madam Foreman,
has the jury reached a verdict?
We have, Your Honor.
Please read the verdict out loud.
"In the case of The People
v. Father Richard Moore...
...we, the jury, find the defendant...
...guilty of negligent homicide."
The court thanks the jury
for its service.
Sentencing for this case
will be set for April 3rd.
Your Honor, if it pleases the court...
...Father Moore requested
at the start of trial...
...that if found guilty,
he would be sentenced immediately.
Yes, I recall that.
Does the prosecution have any
objection to expedited sentencing?
Very well.
Father Richard Moore,
do you understand this sentence...
...which has been found against you?
- Yes, Your Honor.
And do you understand
the gravity of this crime?
That you may, under the law, be
sentenced to a term of up to 10 years?
Yes, I do.
Are there any statements
you wish to make...
...before I impose this sentence?
- No, Your Honor.
- Very well.
Excuse me, Your Honor...
...but the jury would like to make
a recommendation...
...regarding the sentence.
- Objection.
Sit down, counselor.
It's only a recommendation,
and I would like to hear it.
We recommend a sentence
of time served.
I'll accept that.
You are guilty, Father Moore.
And you are free to go.
- This court is dismissed.
- All rise.
Thank you.
Well, you shocked us all.
Everyone at the firm sees this
as another victory.
The archdiocese is pleased.
They feel the trial has raised
public interest in the Church.
Have you seen the news?
There's our priest,
leaving the courthouse a free man...
...right next to you.
Just like James Van Hopper.
All right, I'll say it. I was wrong.
But I'm ready to make it right.
I'm offering you
a full partnership in the firm.
Keep it.
Will you be able to return
to your parish?
I can't go back.
Not now.
Once you've looked
into the darkness...
...I think you carry it with you
for the rest of your life.
What about you?
I believe you've seen
the darkness too.
I don't know.
I'm not sure what I've seen.
- Who chose the epitaph?
- I did.
It's from the second chapter
of Philippians, verse 12.
Emily recited it to me
the night before she died.
Ripped by:
SkyFury